since barack obama became president he
has charged 10 more people with
espionage none of whom have been accused
of giving information to a foreign
government this is all for contact with
journalists that's more than three times
all previous presidents combined it's
nick Sounion is what it is the only hope
that we have because God knows Congress
doesn't have the balls to change this
they have it in the last hundred and
hundred and nine years they're not going
to change it now or 100 and whatever 99
years the only hope we have is twofold
the only way that you can appeal an
espionage conviction is if you go to
trial and our convicted of espionage
there are only two people who fit that
that's chelsea manning and geoffrey
sterling and geoffrey sterling is just
down the road here and what's it called
englewood i think fci englewood daniel
ellsberg who's you know the godfather of
all whistleblowers is leading a
fundraising campaign to raise enough
money to pay for Chelsea Manning's
attorneys so that she can appeal the
Espionage Act convictions it's a it's a
long road and I'm not sure that even the
Supreme Court has the stomach to do it
with that keep my fingers crossed but
with that I went way over I'm looking at
the clock here but let's do some Q&A is
I'm very happy to take your questions
again thank you for having me it's
really my pleasure to be not just in
Colorado but right here in the room with
you today thank you very much thank you
well Cheryl I'm just want to say a word
as treasurer of Fort Collins Community
Action Network I thought I had um that
stp is a part of that umbrella
organization and the turnout today tells
me that there are lots of people very
concerned and very interested and
probably very well informed about some
of the things that are being talked
about if you want these kind of events
to continue to happen then you do need
to support financially strike through
peace and its umbrella organization for
Collins Community Action Network every
year we're needing to find more new
sponsors for our organization to replace
some that leave or for whatever reason
leave the area so please consider if not
giving generously today consider also
being a ongoing sponsor a sustainer and
you can do that by giving us your bank
account number and we'll make it really
easy to take money out of your bank
account for such things you know good
things let us get into your bank account
for good things no but that will help us
sustain the work not only of strength
through peace to bring you these events
but the other ongoing very important
work that we do in this community on the
behalf of poor people on the behalf of
those who need our support and for
progressive change here so thanks for
letting me give that spiel thank you and
if you could keep your questions brief
we'd appreciate that what do you think
that a movie like zero dark thirty oh
all about torture I mean what do you got
just like the National perception that
people have about the CIA's torture
program yeah yeah great question when
zero dark thirty came out I had no
intention whatsoever seeing it and
Daniel Ellsberg called me and he said
you have to see this movie and you have
to write a review because you're the
only one with the moral authority to do
it it was like two days before i left
for prison
so I I didn't see it until I got home
God knows they didn't show us zero dark
thirty in prison I have two thoughts
about that number one the the film
itself I think did the American public a
great disservice because it perpetuated
this lie that torture was what led to
the killing of Osama bin Laden it was
just simply a lie really great analysis
is what led to the the killing of Osama
bin Laden so I I think that Mark Boal
and Kathryn Bigelow really went the
wrong way on that issue I have a friend
who is is very close to Mark Boal and
I'm told that he regrets being involved
in this thing at all I'm glad to hear
that now the other the other point I
want to raise on this and this is where
the CIA goes over the top the CIA
actively collaborates with Hollywood
writers and producers and indeed we know
thanks to the Freedom of Information Act
that when Mark Boal and Kathryn Bigelow
approached the CIA about making the
movie they were given classified
briefings they were given access to a
classified mock-up of the bin Laden
compound and we also have learned
recently that they gave their CIA
interlocutors gifts like watches and
tickets to the premiere that are illegal
now remember what I said the definition
of espionage was providing classified
information or sorry providing national
defense information to any person not
entitled to receive it where are the
charges for Leon Panetta because that's
exactly what he did and then in the
victory lap after the movie was made he
said in a speech in the CIA's auditorium
where Mark Boal was present and other
people who did not have security
clearances Panetta revealed the name of
the SEAL Team six officer who shot bin
Laden ok that is a violation of the
intelligence identities Protection Act
of nineteen eighty-one and I wrote an
op-ed that ran the LA Times saying there
is an empty bunk in myself and Leon
Panetta is perfectly welcome to come and
have it
but there are no charges for Panetta you
know when you're a pal of the President
or you have for shiny stars on your
shoulder or your identified in the New
York Times as the president's favorite
general there are no espionage charges
for you so the whole episode was just a
terrible disservice to the American
people I'm just curious I'm sure you've
heard the recent statements of Donald
Trump criticizing Ted Cruz for not being
hard enough on the position of
waterboarding right so you know I'm not
convinced that the American public is
ever going to come around but of all the
presidential candidates that we have do
you have any hope that any of them might
end up addressing the scituate the you
know what you've described this endemic
a little bit I wrote in a I have a
weekly newspaper column that runs in
small town papers and I wrote a column
last week saying never in my life I've
been a political animal all my life but
never in my life have I ever seen so
many presidential candidates tell us in
advance that they're going to commit an
impeachable act right who does that who
gets up there and says i am going to
commit a war crime as soon as i'm
elected and then Carly Fiorina says I
will too and then Cruz says well I will
too and Rubio said well I'm not sure
okay i will do it sickens me that public
oppose the public opinion polls show
that a majority of Americans support
torture it sickens me and that's one of
the things that makes me feel like I
really need to stay out there talking
about this right the media does say it's
okay but finally yesterday and I saw
this on Facebook of all places former
senior CIA officer said it doesn't
matter who's elected president nobody is
going to get back into the torture
business now the CIA has lied to us
about everything since September 11th
anyway but and I
to believe that that he's telling us the
truth but I think it's up to us to to do
a couple of things to make sure that no
matter who's elected president we don't
return to a torture regime we need to
ride our members of Congress ride them
you know we've got these oversight
committees the Senate Select Committee
on Intelligence and the house permanent
Select Committee on Intelligence they're
supposed to be oversight bodies not
cheerleaders but when you have a new
chairman Senator Richard burr of
Republican of North Carolina for example
say on his first day as chairman that on
his watch there will be no
investigations of the CIA that's not
oversight I mean I understand Frank
church is dead I understand that Pat
Moynihan is dead but by god there has to
be somebody on Capitol Hill with the
guts to stand up to the CIA and say you
work for the American people and we are
the representatives of the American
people and we are going to oversee your
operations and that hasn't happened yet
now in terms of people serious
candidates with a potential to win who I
would trust certainly Bernie Sanders who
I just absolutely adore and i'll tell
you a Bernie story in a second and as
crazy as it sounds Rand Paul I mean Rand
Paul was Rand Paul doesn't mind yet
polling at two percent but he can't win
a Republican primary Bernie Sanders when
I worked for John Kerry on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee staff I
would go down to the Senate cafeteria
every morning and get a bagel and every
single morning there was Bernie sitting
at a table having breakfast and inviting
any Joe who walked in off the street to
sit and have breakfast with him and the
only thing he insisted on was that you
call him Bernie mm-hmm then there were
idiots like you know Ben Cardin the
junior senator from Maryland who would
say I'm a senator coming through I'm
going to the front of the line I'm a
senator and I saw him actually shove a
pregnant woman out of his way so he
could go to the front of the cashiers
line Bernie's not like that
so go Bernie in the intros introduction
she mentioned that you were sort of
recruited by a CIA CIA spotter whose
money are professors yes so I kind of
had sort of basically to the was curious
to the sort of to the extent of your
knowledge how prevalent are these CIA
spotters in academia and how sort of how
common is it that they're recruiting
sort of young students and how does this
relate to this idea you were talking
about about recruiting people with
sociopathic tendencies it's actually
illegal now the way I was recruited has
been illegal since the passage of the
Equal Employment Opportunity Act in 1993
Bill Clinton saw to that but there are
still CIA officers on most campuses at
least most major campuses around the
country they have this thing called the
officer and Residence program so it's a
it's a pre-retirement job for people who
have done their 30 years and want to go
back home so let's say you know you were
born and raised in Bloomington you want
the Indiana University job or you were
born and raised in LA you want the USC
job and then you're going to teach a
couple classes about the CIA or
intelligence or in one case a friend of
mine has one of these positions and is
teaching a course on espionage in Soviet
literature which he's apparently an
expert on so those CIA officers while
there are many of them are overt and
they're there as adjunct or visiting
professors separately the CIA office of
recruitment goes to colleges and
universities constantly and recruits
just like they've done since the 50s
it's much less romantic today you
generally just have to go to ww CIA gov
and click apply now
yeah this is mr. Arne mikoni who is the
Green Party's candidate for United
States Senate for the state of Colorado
I'm very proud to know him I've had the
pleasure to know John over the last year
and I'm honored that I was able to drive
down from Carbondale with my two
children and have my children meet a
national hero I've been to his house in
Arlington and I want to ask a favor I've
met jessalyn through John I've met Tom
Drake through Tom and I I spent ten days
with Daniel Ellsberg and wrote a book
with him Daniel Ellsberg and gotten to
know the whistleblowers these people
have gone way beyond our imagination and
sacrifice and john and geoffrey sterling
should be pardoned by the President of
the United States and if the people are
watching this on television the people
in this room could take some of the
sacrifice out of your time and ask your
representatives and President to
overturn the conviction that John
kyriacou has outlined in this
conversation this is insane thank you
and they need our people need to hear
this tonight there's my question John is
tonight there's a Republican debate it
seems as though the only foreign policy
that's discussed in either the
Democratic or the Republican debate is
counterterrorism your counterterrorism
specialists can you speak to why this
has become the monologue of our foreign
policy in the United States yes people
are easily frightened in our country and
you know we've we've really transitioned
to a permanent wartime economy with the
September love of the tax and I don't
mean to sound conspiratorial because
it's not my nature to be a conspiracy
theorist but I really believe that the
large corporations in this country
can thrive only in this permanent
wartime economy and so we need to
identify an enemy to have at all times
an enemy that we can build up against
and that's why almost none of the
presidential candidates with the
exception of Bernie Sanders are talking
about actually downsizing the military
that's that's the first point my second
point I think would be that another part
of our problem is there really aren't
many differences between the two major
parties I mean they're basically the
same you can tinker around the edges of
some of these issues but look at it this
way especially on national defense and
national security issues in 2002 george
w bush was documented as having killed
one person with the use of a drum okay
barack obama killed 424 people with
drones in october so really what's the
difference between the bush foreign
policy and the obama foreign policy i
would say that the obama foreign policy
is nothing more than a more violent
extension of the bush foreign policy
that's the problem we have in our
presidential candidates not talk not
wanting to talk about anything but
terrorism and one one final point now
that it's popped into my mind again I've
gone nose to nose with al-qaida
nose-to-nose hit another group another
well known terrorist group tried to kill
me in the middle east there were two
assassination attempts against me so I
feel like I know firsthand about
terrorism and I can tell you that that
the the solution to the terrorists
problem is a long-term one and it's one
of education and public works projects
because if these guys that I mentioned
in these isolated villages in their home
countries could read and write and had
job skills and had clean water and maybe
a hospital nearby or roads to get to a
job we wouldn't have this terrorism
problem we wouldn't have to deal with it
it's as simple as that but its long-term
and it's not sexy like an f-35 and a
special stealth you know drone with
extra missiles and it's it's hard sell
people don't want to talk about it
so I was wondering if you're allowed to
disclose the information about the other
and what was at the end ban basically
the torture stuff that you know the
other ten things oh sure yeah they're
they're all in the public record now
okay and and they're listed in the
torture report in their entirety but
they're everything from the basic one
was an open-handed belly slap right
because it makes a loud cracking sound
and it's humiliating it leaves a red
mark that's supposed to be the first
thing that that they do to you and then
they can smack you across the face and
again in the Senate torture report it
specifically said that the middle finger
can't extend beyond the earlobe the palm
can't extend beyond the back half of the
chin it's so very specific and then it
goes to walling and then there was the
confinement box which was either a large
dog cage or a small dog cage sometimes
especially in the case of Abu Zubaydah
they would put him in a dog cage and
then put the dog cage in a cardboard box
so it was dark and he had this
irrational fear of cockroaches and they
would dump cockroaches into the box with
him right and then it progressed its way
up to waterboarding to the cold cell and
when I didn't mention that I should have
which really is one of the really
heinous ones and that sleep deprivation
Donald Rumsfeld famously said in
whenever it was two thousand two
thousand seven I guess that he was
deprived to sleep all the time he would
work 36 hours 48 72 hours with no sleep
and he had a stand-up desk in his office
he wasn't even sitting down when he was
working but the kind of sleep
deprivation we're talking about is your
change that eyebolt in the ceiling again
with hard rock music blasting in on you
24 hours a day those military-grade
halogen lights bearing down on you so
you can't sleep and they keep you up
according to the Senate torture report
for a period not to exceed 16 days okay
we know that people begin losing their
minds at day nine
and people begin to die at day 12 and
the goal is to keep you awake for 16
days if you're lucky you live but you
can't participate in your own defense
because by then you've lost your mind
and others have died and again nobody
was prosecuted what do you think of the
nsa's prodigal childhood and as Edward
Snowden like you know he did come forth
and then we'll now he's in Russia so I
honestly I think it's known as a
national hero I really do I take a lot
of crap for that in a lot of venues but
I think he's done the country of great
national service I might not have
released everything that he released I
actually want us to be intercepting
angouleme Urkel's cell phone that's what
NSA does that's what we want them to do
it whether it's to give us a leg up in
trade negotiations or to disrupt
terrorist attacks we want to be
targeting foreign nationals so I may not
have you know said that but all in all
we wouldn't know that NSA is spying on
us if it weren't for its node and this
this nonsense that that is spouted by
hillary clinton and john kerry that he
defected to Russia he needs to man up
like they've ever been men they he needs
to man up and come and face the music
I've written to him privately through we
share we share some attorneys and I told
him don't come home because in the
Eastern District of Virginia you'll
never get a fair trial never and there's
one judge in particular she was my judge
she was Jeffrey Sterling's judge she
assigned the case of it's known to
herself nobody's ever won with this
judge and I warned him that what the
Justice Department might attempt to do
is they'll say and and he wants to come
home but they'll say all right you do
five years or you do ten years and the
judge will say I don't accept this plea
throw it out and she gives him 40 years
or 30 years because that's what's going
to happen so I think he did a great
national service now this silliness
about him running to Russia defecting to
Russia he was in the transit lounge
Moscow Airport on his way first to
Iceland and then to Latin America when
Hillary Clinton revoked his passport and
he was stuck in that transit lounge for
three weeks if you recall the only
reason he's in Russia is cuz Hillary
Clinton put him there she stuck in there
he had no intention of remaining in
Russia and another thing too and this
became an issue in my case there there's
a Latin term in the legal profession
called mens rea ax it means a guilty
mind criminal intent is what it comes
down to one of the reasons why I was
absolutely convinced I was going to win
my case is because I had no criminal
intent I'm a patriot for God's sake you
know I I've always said that the
Republican Party and the conservative
movement in this country do not have a
monopoly on patriotism so I was
confident I'm gonna win this thing and
on my very first day in my very first
hearing the judge said I will not
respect judge Bennett of the Southern
District of Maryland's decision on mens
rea ax and my attorney said your honor
are you saying that a person can
accidentally commit espionage and she
said that's exactly that's exactly what
I'm saying and my attorneys said this is
going to be a problem and it was you
know same thing with with geoffrey
sterling there was no literally no
evidence that geoffrey sterling
committed a crime but his jury in the
Eastern District of Virginia found him
guilty of nine felonies including seven
counts of espionage for having a
conversation with James verizon of the
New York Times you just don't have a
chance not when not when criminal intent
is not a factor sir my question is if
you hear a comp confidential security
information and you pass it on are you
become liable to if you are a private
citizen yes no that's a great question
that's a very important point good
because I'll defrayed
no and similarly if you are a working
journalist you are not liable for
prosecution unless you are making a
conscious attempt to gather classified
information for the purpose of
distributing it that's that's why
journalists generally aren't prosecuted
now the last attorney general we had
Eric Holder described a fox news
journalist James Rosen as an unindicted
co-conspirator I'd call that a war on
the press you know when instead of being
a journalist doing his job he's an
unindicted co-conspirator you know that
there's a problem with this
administration and these guys are
supposed to be the progressives just
imagine if Ted Cruz's the president
what's going to happen John thank you
very much for your talk my pleasure is
excellent there were a few criticisms I
had of it and one I think you attributed
to someone else which was I just want my
country back from 9-10 right and
actually I want my country back from
1975 from the church commission well I
I'll go back a little further and
actually you can go back you know to the
very foundation in the country but in
1964 the CIA came out with a publication
called khoob our counterintelligence yes
irrigation I believe yes okay somebody
tried to send it to me in prison and the
the warden rejected it as being
disruptive ah um straight through peace
do a little research into this at the
time of the Abu Ghraib scandal to you
know explain that torture actually went
back a long ways from the CIA yes and
the thing that struck me of KU bark is
that the point was to make people feel
that they were damaging themselves so
this threat you put people in stress
positions and they were causing
themselves the pain and so they blame
themselves right it's calm it's called
learned or acquired helplessness you
know much more about it may I'm sure
but but so could you comment on how how
does what was going on in qu bark
compared to what happened after 911 are
we in a qualitatively worse era and how
so that's my after nine eleven it became
more more regimented and more formal and
it was more it was better documented the
CIA this has been a cyclical issue for
the CIA over the years the CIA did some
terrible terrible things in the 1950s
and 60s for example the prices of which
we're still paying today I mean the
overthrow of masada in Iran we're still
we're still dealing with the
ramifications of that terrible operation
look look at the trouble that the CIA
has caused in Latin America over the
years guatemala el salvador nicaragua
the dominican republic were still
feeling that the after-effects of those
operations so we've go through these
periods where torture is okay and then
tortures not okay again probably the the
golden age for civil libertarians was in
the immediate aftermath of the church
committee hearings where there really
was oversight in fact in the aftermath
of church Senator Daniel Patrick
Moynihan of New York wrote a book a very
well received critically acclaimed book
saying there there's no need for a CIA
anymore certainly the Directorate of
operations can be folded into the
department's defense Human Services they
do human source collection and the
analytic arm of the CIA the Directorate
of intelligence can be folded into the
State Department's Bureau of
intelligence and research and then the
Directorate of Science and Technology
can be split between the Pentagon and
NASA there's no need to have a CI
anymore you know John Kennedy played
with that idea and took two bullets to
the head and I'm not saying that the CIA
killed Kennedy I'm just saying at the
time of the Kennedy assassination
cetera et cetera okay when I joined the
CIA before I joined the CIA I went to a
classmate of mine in grad school and I
knew that her boyfriend was at the CIA
and I asked if I could have dinner with
him so we got together and I said listen
I was just talking this guy he's
pitching me for the CIA but I have some
concerns about the bad old days and I
want to hear your side of the story and
he said oh yeah that's that's all in the
past since the church committee it's
been great we don't do any of that stuff
anymore I said all right and then
honestly everything seemed to me to be
okay again I was a junior analyst so I
really didn't have a full view of what
was happening but then when bill clinton
was elected the CIA went through this
this culling of sources anybody who had
any any his any history of human rights
abuses was was fired from the payroll
right and they got rid of something like
a third of their sources and i thought
you know this is great this is exactly
the way it should be we shouldn't have
people on the payroll who are torturers
you know generals with human rights
issues in their past etc and that was
that worked until September 11th and
then all the rules went out the window
and everything no matter how crazy it
sounded was appropriate if you could
make an argument that it's somehow made
Americans safer and we've never come
back from that it's become the norm
which is really dangerous I've read your
letters from prison on the common dreams
website terrific him and the question
that kept coming to my mind was I
wondered if your identity was known
widely or at all to the fellow prisoners
because sometimes accounts that come out
of prison or that there's punishment and
then there's the brutality that is
visited on somebody who is labeled or
tagged as a traitor to the country
causing American boys to be killed etc
etc so I wondered how that for thank you
for that question I love talking about
this
everybody in the prison knew who I was
before I arrived several hundred
prisoners get the new york times i was
on the front page of the of the sunday
times the week before i arrived in
prison so everybody knew so several
things happened virtually all in my
first week when I when I turned myself
in well I should back up at sentencing
the judge ordered that I'd be sent to a
minimum-security work camp Club fed as
they as they miss identify it the press
and you know Club fed it there's no
fence there are no walls you can work in
town you just have to be on your honored
oh you know come back on time so I got
to prison my first day and I went over
to the camp and I said hi I'm John
Kiriakou I'm here to turn myself in the
guy says everybody has to check in
across the street the prison I said okay
my attorneys i went up to prison with
jessalyn raid act Tom Drake Jim spean
who directed and produced the
documentary film silenced my cousin and
his son-in-law so we took this big van
up there they dropped me off hugs kisses
goodbye they drove away I go across the
street to prison I said hi I'm John
Kerry hago here to turn myself in the
guy looks his computer he says okay he
said turn around put your hands behind
your back I put my hands behind my back
he cuffs me then he shackles my ankles
and he said okay let's go and I said
well wait a minute I'm supposed to be at
the camp across the street and he said
not according to my paperwork you're not
so I thought oh my god they're putting
me in the actual prison take it easy
there's nothing you can do if you make a
scene they'll put you in solitary it was
five days before I was allowed to make a
phone call so I called my attorneys and
I said listen they put me in the actual
prison which was a low-security prison
but which means double walls concertina
wire controlled moves the whole nine
yards murderers mostly pedophiles but
lots of murderers who
and he said well we can file a motion
but it'll be two years before we get
hearing you're just going to have to
tough it out so I was in prison well the
only thing that the guard told me as I
was checking in was hey buddy he said
one of the most important rules is if
somebody comes in to your cell uninvited
that's an act of aggression and I
thought great I'm 50 years old I'm going
to have to defend my I'm gonna get my
ass kicked on the very first day in
prison so I'm sitting on the edge of my
bed and these two Aryans walk into my
room just walk right in big swastikas on
their necks one guy had tattooed fu so
every time he blinked yeah how do you
like that in a job interview after he
gets out of prison so I jumped off the
bed and I said what do you want and one
of them says take it easy he says are
you a and I said no and he said are
you a rat and I said no I'm not a rat I
didn't have anybody in my case are you a
chomo I said I don't know what that
means he says chomo like I'm stupid
child molester I said no I'm not a child
molester so he said okay you considered
our table in the cafeteria and I thought
oh I guess I'm with the Aryans now so
few days later these two big
muscle-bound black guys come into my
cell and the same thing I jumped up I
said what do you want one guy puts his
hands up he said are you the CIA guy I
said yeah and he's holding this
newspaper and he said Reverend Farrakhan
says you're a hero of the Muslim people
and we wanted to tell you that you're
not going to have any trouble with us
and I said okay thanks I said thanks I
appreciate it and he says I don't shake
hands with the white devil I said I'm
sorry I said I said thank you I
appreciate you coming in and then
finally I was across the hall from a
from a senior captain in the Bonanno
crime family and when I was done with my
new york times i would give them to him
and he would give me his new york post
so we kind of struck up this friendship
to the port where he said to me one day
yeah I'm in on a murder charge somebody
found a body in a barrel in my student
on my storage unit he said I don't know
how his body got in there like a hundred
people had access to my storage unit I
said Pete you don't have to explain your
case to me I don't care how the body got
in your storage unit anyway he said to
me one day let me ask you a question why
do you sit with those retards in the
cafeteria I said I don't know they they
invited me my first day here and he says
from today you're with the Italians so I
said thank you we had the actual boss of
the Gambino crime family Little Nicky
carazzo we had Peter the rebbe at
Calabrese we had the boss of the Cal
vacante family we had the Genovese
families captain who ran the port of
Newark and I was friends with all these
guys there was one thing though Little
Nicky he's doing 18 years on 18 murders
how he must had a brilliant lawyer I
don't know but anyway yeah so I I stayed
away from Nikki because he had a
reputation as being obviously very
violent and then one day one of his
bodyguards came up to my room and a huge
guy like stupid cross-eyed and he says
the boss wants to see you and I thought
oh my god because I've been trying like
not to make eye contact with the guy
everybody else was great to me I go down
to his room and I said mr. carrozza did
you want to see me and he says you two
CIA guy I said I am you write a book I
said I did your book do good I said
actually it did very well I made number
five on the New York Times bestseller
list it was my first book
he goes you're gonna write my book I
said oh is that what this is about and
he says I'm going to tell you stories
and you're gonna write them down I said
well let's think about this for a second
you know most of the books of this genre
written by rats and they spend the first
half of the book talking about all the
cool things they did but they spend the
second half of the book trying to
justify why they turn rap and you're not
a rat and you probably shouldn't talk
about all the cool stuff you've done I
wouldn't write the book and he says
hadn't thought of that nevermind but
then from that day I was invited to
every Italian dinner every Italian party
birthday parties going away parties they
had a crooked cop on the payroll we had
pork loins and lamb chops and white wine
for the marsala sauce and fresh
mushrooms and tomatoes and Alfredo I
gained 15 pounds in prison I did 15
pounds the cops have come in what are
you guys cooking today oh we got some
nice veal veal chops here wow really
smells good yeah it does so the Italians
to Cara Mia there was one Italian in
particular who really became my closest
friend I actually miss his friendship
very much we're not allowed to have
contact because that would be consorting
with known felons which means I would go
directly back to prison so he had read
about my case in advance and took it
upon himself to engage with every one of
the Italians at loretto to explain to
them the difference between the CIA and
the FBI right the FBI are rats and cops
the CIA are heroes who protect the
country overseas and so as soon as these
Italians understood that I didn't have
arrest powers and I would never ratted
on anybody I was one of them
and it made life very very very easy I'm
writing a book about this I finished it
actually it's out for bid it's called
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison and
there's one there's one account of I was
near the end of my of my sentence and my
my bunkmate was the former mayor of
Cleveland right awesome guy totally
corrupt just like a big brother to me
was so great so he said to me one day
hey John there was some guy in the
insulin line tonight talking trash about
you he said you were a rat I said who
who said I was a wreck those are
fighting words he said I don't know I
never saw him before and then sure
enough another friend of mine from Texas
came down and said that there's this guy
in the cafeteria telling people you're a
rat I said point him out to me I want to
see who this guy is and they pointed him
out to me in the cafeteria and I shouted
at him I said hey you have a problem
with me and the guy says you know what I
said you know where I live you come up
to my room and we'll finish this between
the two of us I said right now I told
him well the only place where the cops
feel vulnerable is in the cafeteria
because you have 1400 guys and ten cops
right so they're always worried about
violence breaking out I stood up I said
let's go right now I had no intention
really I was I was bluffing so um one of
the Aryans came over and he said please
please not in here though they'll arrest
all of us and put us all in solitary
well Peter the rabbit Calabrese was next
to me and he looks up he says what are
you doing sit down he says we'll take
care of this later so I'm staring at
this guy and I said as God is my witness
Pete I'm gonna kill this guy and I don't
know why I was so angry nobody had ever
called me a rat before but this guy
maintained that I had ratted out the CIA
by talking about torture so I sat down
and then Pete says we're going to go
back to my room and you're going to read
the USA today so I was shaking I was so
angry we went back to his room
he hands me the USA Today he says I'll
be back in a minute so he and another
Italian went out and they came back 20
minutes later and he said to me it's all
taken care of I said what's that
supposed to mean he said it means don't
worry about it it's all taken care of I
said all right all right I said I trust
you I gave him back his paper and I went
to my cell about 20 minutes later the
guy comes down to my room and his face
is like this and there's blood coming
out of his nose and blood coming out of
his lip and he says to me I'm very sorry
for calling you rat I don't know why I
did it I'll never say it again I said
get out of my room before I kill you and
he went back to his room and there was
never any problem again after that
because i had the italians to rely on i
read some time ago that former President
Truman wrote a letter to Washington
posted i think 1963 that his greatest
mistake was signing the CIA i've read
that and is it the Washington Post as I
understand printed it in their first
edition and then pulled it out on the
later yes yeah interestingly enough J
Edgar Hoover was the one that put it
into Truman's ear that this creation of
the CIA was a terrible terrible mistake
now Hoover was saying that for his own
purposes of course because when when
Congress first began considering the
National Security Act of 1947 whoever
just assumed that the CIA was going to
be a division within the FBI and when
general Donovan insisted to Truman and
Donovan had Truman's ear when he
insisted to Truman that the CIA be an
independent standalone agency Hoover
turned and tried to talk the president
into first not signing the bill and then
later to disbanding the CIA in the next
national security authorization act it
didn't work and we've been stuck with
the CIA ever since I have a two-part
question so the first part of my
question
I agree that ethics should be introduced
back into politics and other areas as
well besides just intelligence
operations but I was curious if you've
ever thought about the steps that need
to be taken to introduce ethics into
intelligence operations um and then a
second part of my question and forget my
ignorance on your opinion in your
position but do you think the torture
program needs to be completely
eradicated or like do you think there is
some good that comes out of it and it
just needs to be reorganized I'll answer
the second part first because that's an
easy one no I think tortures
inappropriate under all circumstances
there's no place for it it doesn't work
it's not moral it's not ethical it's not
legal we have this federal torture act
that bans it we have we're signatories
to the united nations convention against
torture and indeed not only were we the
original signatories we were actually
the authors of the united nations
convention against torture and let me
add another thing to that in in the
january of 1968 The Washington Post ran
a front-page picture of an American
soldier waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner when the secretary of defense
robert mcnamara saw that picture he
ordered an investigation and the soldier
was arrested and he was tried and
convicted of torture and he was
imprisoned well the law hasn't changed
since nineteen sixty eight so why was
torture illegal in 1968 but not illegal
in 2002 or in 2015 you know when when we
had to pass the McCain fine stein
amendment to reaffirm our national ban
on torture so the law never changed
American politics changed we need to
change it back in terms of how we
implement ethics into our political
system I think there are two ways to do
it one is Congress has very very strict
ethics regulations and both houses of
Congress have an ethics committee that
is not only to advise the members of
Congress on ethics but every staff
member on Capitol Hill I can't tell you
how many times I had to engage the
Ethics Committee on sometimes very basic
questions but that's what they're there
for if there's any question at all you
just ask the ethics people what to do
and they
what's the right thing what's the wrong
thing so I think that that needs to
extend to the executive branch I think
every federal department and agency like
they have a general counsel and they
have an inspector general ought to have
a chief ethics officer justice does
although the Bush administration
bastardized the the position but I think
every governmental agency should have a
chief ethics officer another thing is
that lots of colleges and universities
across the country especially Catholic
schools have very robust ethics programs
ethics departments in many cases and I
think we need to rely on those people to
guide us in government as to what proper
ethical processes are not just in
intelligence operations but in any
governmental function at all you know
they're they're experts in ethics and we
should rely on that expertise John thank
you so much for your presentation thing
because this has been very very helpful
this is the kind of thing I think that
we need much more of rather than the
circus that's going on right now with
the presidential candidates agree but I
wanted to ask you if you had a magic
wand and you could really revise the
whole approach in this area of Foreign
Affairs what would you do what would be
your suggestions fares writ large well
and end CIA and the interaction between
those this is just a short question yes
you know I'm so arrogant that I've never
been stumped before I'm stumped now in a
perfect world the scituate the setup
that we have ought to work it's not a
perfect world and for the most part I
think I blame Congress their Congress
just over the deck
aids I mean through generations Congress
doesn't lead their reactive reactionary
there's really no oversight and it's
both parties and they lie you know when
I was a when I was in college I used to
be an autograph hound and my college
roommate and I would each buy copies of
the Almanac of American politics we
didn't have friday classes so every
Friday we would go up to Capitol Hill
and we would get autographs from famous
senators and congressmen right and I
have you know some of the Giants Barry
Goldwater Ted Kennedy Bob Dole scoop
Jackson mo Udall was loads of fun and I
I thought these guys were special
because the country had entrusted them
with leading us and you know now I
realize how naive and how childish that
was that for the most part they're
idiots they're just idiots and they're
opportunists on top of it so when you
have the likes of dianne feinstein you
know just cheering for the CIA and
approving of the torture program and
then when things hit the fan saying well
jeez I I don't think I was briefed on
that and they say well yeah you were
maybe a staff member forgot to give me
the notes no you were there and we have
a record of you being there I just don't
remember well that's not leadership
that's not oversight you know when when
Diane Feinstein says I don't know if I
like Leon Panetta as director we need
somebody who really knows intelligence
so al vote for Panetta only if Steve
Capus gets to be the deputy director
well Steve Capus was one of the
architects of the torture program so
thanks to Diane Feinstein we have this
you know can add this continuing legacy
of torture another problem is all the
senior CIA leaders of the Bush
administration were the senior CIA
leaders of the Obama administration
there are civil servants they didn't go
anywhere and they know that they can
outwait presidents presidents are going
to be there for four years or eight
years these guys are going to be there
for 35 years so they can just wait so
really I think that the problem that we
have had is a problem of
congressional leadership you know the
CIA just by its nature is going to try
to get away with as much as it possibly
can but that's what oversight is all
about oversight is a committee saying
wait a minute no you can't do that you
can't overthrow that government you
can't establish that secret prison
another problem is when the CIA
determines that an operation is so
sensitive or so classified it only
informs the chairman and vice-chairman
of the two committees right that's
considered to be notification but if the
chairman and vice-chairman of the
committee's are true believers and
cheerleaders then again there is no
oversight so it's all about Congress in
my view well thank you very much what a
pleasure it is to be here I really
appreciate it thanks for everything
thank you
so I also wanted to let you know that
it's going to be broadcast on Fort
Collins public media so thanks to
Phillip mayor for videotaping it for us
and when that comes out on Fort Collins
public media I'll let you know via
social media and our listserv so you can
tune in and let your friends know